Finding Aid for Andy Kirk papers, 1923-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Andy Kirk papers 1923-1991, 1935-1950
Kirk, Andy, 1898-1992.
1.75 linear foot
2010210 Aa 2
African American musician and bandleader Andy Kirk began a career that spanned more than thirty years in 1919, when he joined the George Morrison Orchestra as a saxophonist. He went on to earn renown as a bandleader and musician within the Big Band and Jazz genres. The Andy Kirk papers include photographs, newspaper clippings, correspondence, and the rough draft manuscript for his autobiography 20 Years on Wheels.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Andy Kirk Papers were received in September 2008 through the University of Michigan Center for Afro-American and African Studies (donor 10110 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Andrew Kirk was born May 28th 1898, in Newport, Kentucky. According to family lore, although the family lived in Cincinnati, Ohio, Kirk's mother wanted her son to be born in her native Kentucky and she crossed the river to the nearby city of Newport. Kirk's mother died when he was three years old and his Aunt Mary adopted him. The family moved to Denver, Colorado in 1904 where jobs were reported to be more plentiful.
Kirk took music lessons as a child and his music teacher at the Denver Public Schools was Wilberforce Whiteman, the father of musician and bandleader Paul Whiteman. Kirk bought a saxophone and began taking lessons. In 1919, he joined the George Morrison Orchestra as a saxophonist. It was during this time that he began dating Mary Colston a pianist and fellow musician. They married in 1925. That same year Kirk moved to Dallas, Texas to join a band led by Terrance Holder called the Dark Clouds of Joy. In 1928, Holder left the band and Kirk was elected as its new bandleader. The band changed its name to Andy Kirk and the Twelve Clouds of Joy. Shortly thereafter, the band auditioned for the Pal-Mor Ballroom in Kansas City. At that time, Kansas City was something of a hub for jazz musicians and the move proved to be successful for the band. They began recording and were engaged for a six-week performance at the Roseland Ballroom in New York. Mary Lou Williams, wife of the band's saxophone player, began filling in on piano. Eventually she became the band's full-time pianist and sometime music arranger. Williams became famous in her own right first as a member of the band and later with a solo career. In 1929, Andy Kirk Jr. was born.
The band began touring in the 1930s. 1936 proved to be a successful year for the band with a couple of hit songs including Until the Real Thing Comes Along the song for which the Twelve Clouds of Joy is best known. Over the years, the band featured many prominent, or soon to be prominent, musicians including Fats Navaro, Hattie McDaniel, Mary Lou Williams, June Richardson, Charlie Parker, Dick Wilson, and Lester Young.
The decline in the popularity of big band music in the late 1940s led to the Clouds of Joy disbanding in 1948.
Kirk received his real estate license in the 1950s and later was the manager of the Theresa Hotel in Harlem, New York. Kirk, however, continued to play with bands in his free time. In later life, he became a devoted Jehovah's Witness and worked for the church for many years. In 1977, Kirk began to write his memoirs. The resulting book was published in 1989 by the University of Michigan Press and entitled 20 Years on Wheels after one of the songs he had written. Kirk was honored in 1991 as an American Jazz Master by the National Endowment for the Arts. He donated his $20,000 American Jazz Master Fellowship to the Adam Clayton Powell Junior High in Harlem, New York. Andy Kirk passed away December 11th 1992, of complications from Alzheimer's disease.
The Andy Kirk Papers are comprised of newspaper clippings, photographs, correspondence, and personal papers which document the career of musician and bandleader Andy Kirk. The collection covers the years 1923 to 1991 but most of the materials are from Kirk's active career within the years 1935 and 1950. The collection was initially processed by the Center for Afro-American and African Studies. It is divided into eight series: Correspondence, Writings, Legal Papers, Photographs, Scripts, Clippings, Ephemera, and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Kirk, Andy, 1898-1992.; Twelve Clouds of Joy (Musical group); African American musicians.; Band leaders.; Jazz musicians--United States.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Kirk, Andy, 1898-1991.; Twelve Clouds of Joy (Musical group); African American musicians.; Jazz musicians--United States.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence 1935-1991
  The Correspondence series (.25 linear feet) covers the years 1935 to 1991 and is arranged alphabetically. Items in this series include letters of a professional and personal nature written to and by Kirk. Also included are several very well preserved telegrams sent to Kirk.
  - Telegrams 1935-1942, 1945-1948, 1950, undated, 14 folders (Box 1)
  - Postcard 1968 (Box 1)
  - Letters 1968-1991, undated, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Watchtower Bible and Tract Society 1965-1966 (Box 1)
- Writings 1976-1990
  The Writings series (.15 linear feet) encompasses the years from 1976 to 1990 and is arranged alphabetically. The subseries 20 Years on Wheels includes notes on Kirk's autobiography, correspondence between Kirk and his writer Amy Lee, and a final manuscript of the book.
  - 20 Years on Wheels
    - Correspondence with Amy Lee 1977-1987 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1977-1989, undated (Box 1)
    - Tentative Prospectus 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Notes on Book Cover (Box 1)
    - Notes on Early Chapters (Box 1)
    - Sample Anecdotes undated (Box 1)
    - Prologue and Introduction undated (Box 1)
    - Final Manuscript, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Book Reviews 1990 (Box 1)
- Legal Papers 1946-1990
  The Legal Papers series (.10 linear feet) covers the years 1946-1990 and is arranged alphabetically. The series has files relating to Kirk's copyrights, performance contracts, and royalties.
  - Correspondence 1985-1990 (Box 1)
  - Songwriter's Contracts 1944-1966 (Box 1)
  - Recording Contracts 1945-1954 (Box 1)
  - Performance Agreements for American Guild of Variety Artists and King's Majestic Corporation 1956 & 1989 (Box 1)
  - Copyrights 1946-1969 (Box 1)
  - Royalties 1945-1958 & undated (Box 1)
- Photographs 1924-1971, 1990
  The Photographs series (.50 linear feet) has photographs dated from 1924 to 1971 as well as a fair amount of undated materials. It is arranged alphabetically. Photographs include publicity shots of Kirk, his orchestra, and fellow musicians many of which are autographed. There are also several personal and familial photographs. The subseries Scenes includes photographs from Kirk's two movies Killer Diller and Going Places.
  - 92nd Birthday Celebration (Box 1)
  - Andy Kirk with June Richmond (Box 1)
  - Andy Kirk with Louis Armstrong (Box 1)
  - Andy Kirk with Nat King Cole at the Phonograph Merchants Luncheon 1945 (Box 1)
  - Andy Kirk with Unidentified Individuals (Box 1)
  - Children (Box 1)
  - Congregation of the First Baptist Church -- Cincinnati, Ohio 1931 (Box 1)
  - Early Wheels -- George Morrison Band 1924 (Box 1)
  - Ella Fitzgerald (Autographed) (Box 1)
  - European Travels (Box 1)
  - Family, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Group Photographs of Twelve Clouds of Joy Orchestra (Box 1)
  - Harry S. Truman at Teresa Hotel undated (Box 1)
  - Hattie McDaniel (Autographed) 1944 & undated (Box 1)
  - Individuals and Groups with Andy Kirk (Box 1)
  - Individuals and Groups without Andy Kirk (Box 1)
  - Individual Photographs of Andy Kirk (Box 1)
  - Individual Photographs of Twelve Clouds of Joy Orchestra Members (Box 1)
  - J.D. Fields (Box 1)
  - Joe Attles (Box 1)
  - Mary Lou Williams (Autographed) 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Negatives (Box 1)
  - Publicity Shots of Groups, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Publicity Shots of Groups with Unidentified Individuals (Box 1)
  - Publicity Shots of Individuals, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Publicity Shots of Unidentified Individuals (Box 2)
  - Watchtower Kingdom Ministry School 1971 & undated (Box 2)
  - Weddings (Box 2)
  - Scenes
    - All American Pictures – Killer Diller (Box 2)
    - Warner Brothers – Going Places (Box 2)
- Scripts 1940-1949
  The Scripts series (.10 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically and covers the years 1940-1949. It is comprised of scripts from radio performances and announcing jobs. A subseries Armed Forces Radio Services contains scripts from radio performances by Andy Kirk and his Orchestra during wartime via the Armed Forces Radio.
  - Armed Forces Radio Service
    - Downbeat # 74 (Box 2)
    - Jubilee # 66 1944 (Box 2)
    - Jubilee # 67 1944 (Box 2)
    - Jubilee # 69 1944 (Box 2)
    - Jubilee # 133 1945 (Box 2)
    - Jubilee # 134 1945 (Box 2)
    - Jubilee # 135 1945 (Box 2)
  - Men With Batons 1940 (Box 2)
  - Rose Meta House of Beauty Sixth Annual Hair Style Show (Box 2)
  - Rose Meta House of Beauty Spring and Summer Hair Styles Show 1949 (Box 2)
  - Rose Meta House of Beauty Lily Production, Rockland Palace 1949 (Box 2)
  - Victory Parade of Spotlight Bands 1943-1945, 5 folders (Box 2)
- Clippings 1936-1992
  The Clippings series (.10 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically and includes newspaper clippings dated from 1936 to 1992. Items cover Kirk's career, the careers of fellow musicians, and other items of Big Band or Jazz interest. Kirk's obituary is included in the clippings. Several of the clippings are original, but a number of the items are photocopies.
  - Andy Kirk and His Orchestra 1941-1991 (Box 2)
  - Andy Kirk and His Orchestra (Photocopies) 1936-1992 (Box 2)
  - Mary Lou Williams 1946-1981 & undated (Box 2)
  - Mary Lou Williams (Photocopies) 1970-1979 & undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Removed (Box 2)
- Ephemera 1946-1990
  The Ephemera series (.15 linear feet), 1946-1990 is arranged alphabetically and is largely comprised of items collected by Kirk. Materials in this series include programs, promotional materials, prayer cards and programs from friend's funerals, and promotional stamps issued of Andy Kirk.
  - American Jazz Orchestra Concert 1990 (Box 2)
  - Certificate of Award Washington Heights Boys League 1968 & 1975 (Box 2)
  - Flyers (Box 2)
  - Invitations (Box 2)
  - Jazzology Magazine September 1946 (Box 2)
  - Non-Postal Promotional Stamp & Postcard of Andy Kirk undated (Box 2)
  - Personal Directories of Andy Kirk (Box 2)
  - Poster of Killer Diller (Box 2)
  - Prayer Cards and Funeral Programs 1955-1984 (Box 2)
  - Program of the Benefit for the 110th Street Community Center 1948 (Box 2)
  - Program for "I too Sing for America," 1990 (Box 2)
  - Promotional Materials (Box 2)
- Topical Files 1946-1990
  The Topical Files series (.40 linear feet) encompasses the years 1923-1983 and is arranged alphabetically. Items in this series were collected by Kirk and include Jazz magazines, programs, publications, promotional materials, and personal papers.
  - Carnegie Hall Programs (Box 2)
  - Flyers (Box 2)
  - Fragments, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Joe Attles Legal Documents (Box 2)
  - Joe Attles Papers (Box 2)
  - Musical Score "Keep the Home-Fires Burning" (Box 2)
  - Storyville 70 1977 (Box 2)
  - The Swing Era: 1939-1940 1939 A Real Dream of an Era, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Theatre Programs (Porgy & Bess) (Box 2)
  - Unidentified Journal 1923-1924, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Unidentified Journal 1932-1935, 4 folders (Box 2)